{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of a growth curve?", "opta": "Shows development of microbial population under relatively stable environmental conditions", "optb": "Plotted with logarithmic numbers", "optc": "Graphs numbers of microbes versus time", "optd": "Each growth curve consists of four distinct phases", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Generation time of Escherichia coli is", "opta": "20 minutes", "optb": "20 hours", "optc": "20 days", "optd": "200 hours", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The organism which obtain their energy from chemicals are designated as", "opta": "prototrophs", "optb": "chemotrophs", "optc": "organotrophs", "optd": "autotrophs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nutrient content and biological structures are considered as", "opta": "implicit factor for microbial growth", "optb": "intrinsic factor for microbial growth", "optc": "processing factor", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The organism which grows best above 45\u00b0C are called", "opta": "psychrophilic", "optb": "mesosphilic", "optc": "thermophilic", "optd": "any of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Implicit factors", "opta": "depend on developing microflora", "optb": "can be synergistic", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lag phase is also known as", "opta": "period of initial adjustment", "optb": "transitional period", "optc": "generation time", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used to grow bacterial cultures continuously?", "opta": "Chemostat", "optb": "Coulter Counter", "optc": "Hemostat", "optd": "Petroff-Hausser chamber", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A microbe, which grows at temperatures above 95\u00b0 C is most likely to be", "opta": "an archaean", "optb": "a fungus", "optc": "a protozoan", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some organisms can use reduced inorganic compounds as electron donors and are termed as", "opta": "lithotrophs", "optb": "phototrophs", "optc": "chemotrophs", "optd": "photo-organotrophs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total biomass of an organism will be determined by the nutrient present in the lowest concentration relative to the organism's requirements is a statement of", "opta": "Liebig's law of the minimum", "optb": "Shelford's law of tolerance", "optc": "quorum sensing", "optd": "Heisenberg's principle of uncertainty", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The growth is normally expressed as __________ in turbidimetric measurement", "opta": "cells per ml", "optb": "cfu/ml", "optc": "optical density", "optd": "mg N2 /ml", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following organisms typically get their carbon for biosynthesis from carbon dioxide?", "opta": "Glucose-fermenting bacteria (fermentation)", "optb": "Anaerobic, glucose-respiring bacteria (anaerobic respiration)", "optc": "Aerobic, glucose-respiring bacteria (aerobic respiration)", "optd": "Ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (chemolithotrophic bacteria)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An organism that expends energy to grow in a habitat with a low water activity in order to maintain internal solute concentrations to retain water is", "opta": "osmotolerant", "optb": "acidophile", "optc": "aerotolerant anaerobe", "optd": "alkalophile", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The straightforward method of binary fission explains how bacteria", "opta": "grow in nutrient agar", "optb": "evolve", "optc": "move", "optd": "reproduce", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The equation used to obtain bacterial population by binary fission is", "opta": "N = No2n", "optb": "log N/No = (0.3010) n", "optc": "log(N/No) = nlog 2", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bacteria and fungi multiply best", "opta": "below 16\u00b0C", "optb": "between 16-38\u00b0C", "optc": "above 38\u00b0C", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An organism has an optimal growth rate when the hydrogen ion concentration is very high. This organism is", "opta": "osmotolerant", "optb": "acidophile", "optc": "neutrophile", "optd": "aerotolerant anaerobe", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following procedures uses a photocell to measure absorbance of a culture to regulate the flow of culture media?", "opta": "Coulter Counter", "optb": "Hemostat", "optc": "Petroff-Hausser chamber", "optd": "Trubidostat", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Organisms, using organic compounds as electron donors are called", "opta": "lithotrophs", "optb": "phototrophs", "optc": "chemotrophs", "optd": "organotrophs", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reproduction by budding occur in", "opta": "Rhodopseudomonas acidophila", "optb": "Hyphomicrobium vulgare", "optc": "Bacillus subtilis", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Starvation proteins are produced by a culture during which of the following segments of the growth curve?", "opta": "Lag phase", "optb": "Exponential phase", "optc": "Stationary phase", "optd": "Death phase", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cell reproduction in bacteria may occur by", "opta": "binary fission", "optb": "budding", "optc": "fragmentation", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During exponential growth, the growth rate is", "opta": "number of generations per unit time", "optb": "reciprocal of generation time", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A spore differs from an actively replicating bacterium in that the spore", "opta": "is produced during a process involving asymmetric division", "optb": "is able to withstand more extreme conditions than the replicating cell", "optc": "is metabolically inactive", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has more tolerance for acidic pH (lower pH)?", "opta": "Yeast and moulds", "optb": "Bacteria", "optc": "E. coli", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ability of Vibrio fischeri to produce bioluminescence chemicals only when a certain population density has been reached is an example of", "opta": "Liebig's law of the minimum", "optb": "Shelford's law of tolerance", "optc": "quorum sensing", "optd": "Heisenberg's principle of uncertainty", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Antimicrobial constituents for the microbial growth in foods are", "opta": "intrinsic factor", "optb": "extrinsic factor", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The average size of cells during the exponential phase of growth is", "opta": "greater than the lag phase", "optb": "lesser than the lag phase", "optc": "equal to the lag phase", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A culture broth tube was very turbid at the surface but clear throughout the rest of the tube indicating that the", "opta": "organism are aerobes", "optb": "organism should be grown in an anaerobic chamber", "optc": "organism cannot produce superoxide dismutase and/or catalase", "optd": "organism cannot tolerate oxygen", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A synergistic effect is observed when", "opta": "one organism removes an inhibitory substance for another", "optb": "one organism produces a growth factor utilized by another", "optc": "microbial alteration of pH, aw, Eh favours the growth of another", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Generation time is", "opta": "time required for the population to double", "optb": "time required for the initial adjustment", "optc": "obtained by expression t/n, where t = time interval, n = number of generation", "optd": "both (a) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term facultative anaerobe refers to an organism that", "opta": "doesn't use oxygen but tolerates it", "optb": "is killed by oxygen", "optc": "uses oxygen when present or grows without oxygen when absent", "optd": "requires less oxygen than is present in air", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The microorganisms that grow best in a low-oxygen environment is called a (n)", "opta": "aerobe", "optb": "anaerobe", "optc": "facultative", "optd": "microaerophile", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pseudomonas pseudoflava can grow as", "opta": "chemo-lithotrophs", "optb": "chemo-organotrophs", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the suitable temperature range for mesophiles?", "opta": "20-30\u00b0C", "optb": "25-40\u00b0C", "optc": ">40\u00b0C", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exponential phase of growth curve of bacteria is of limited duration because of", "opta": "rise in cell density", "optb": "accumulation of toxic metabolites", "optc": "exhaustion of nutrients", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A culture broth tube was very turbid at the bottom of the tube but clear at the top of the tube indicating that the", "opta": "broth is sterile", "optb": "organism can tolerate oxygen", "optc": "organism cannot produce superoxide dismutase and/or catalase", "optd": "organism should be grown in an anaerobic chamber", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the exponential phase, the cells and cell mass", "opta": "first increases then decreases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "are constant", "optd": "double at a constant rate", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the primary source of food for marine life?", "opta": "Phytoplankton", "optb": "Zooplankton", "optc": "Sea weed", "optd": "Grass", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Postgates assay technique is useful in determining if a cell is viable even though it is", "opta": "incapable of cell division", "optb": "too small to see", "optc": "an obligate aerobe", "optd": "a thermophile", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What are the extrinsic factors for the microbial growth?", "opta": "humidity", "optb": "storage temperature", "optc": "composition of gas phase", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Quantitative measurement of bacterial growth can be carried out by measuring", "opta": "cell count", "optb": "cell mass", "optc": "cell activity", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Organisms such as lactobacilli that have elaborate requirements for specific nutrients i.e. vitamins and other growth promoting substances, are generally called as", "opta": "fastidious hetrotrophs", "optb": "chemo-lithotrophs", "optc": "chemotrophs", "optd": "photo-organotrophs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The combination of low levels of NaCl, NaNO3 (sodium nitrate), and slightly acid pH can prevent multiplication and toxin formation of", "opta": "Salmonella", "optb": "S. aureus", "optc": "C. botulinum", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bacteria of genus Nitrosomonas use __________ as their electron source.", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "H2S", "optc": "succinate", "optd": "light", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All organisms require at least small amounts of carbondioxide, However, some can use CO2 as their sole source of carbon. Such organisms are termed as", "opta": "autotrophs", "optb": "phototrophs", "optc": "chemotrophs", "optd": "photo-organotrophs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The generation time of a culture that produces two generations per hour is", "opta": "greater than that produces three generations per hour", "optb": "lesser than that produces three generations per hour", "optc": "equal to that produces three generations per hour", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Autotrophic bacteria are those which", "opta": "make their own food", "optb": "form a long chain glycocalyx", "optc": "are highly susceptible to penicillin", "optd": "produce a blue-green pigment", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following organisms typically get their carbon for biosynthesis from organic compounds?", "opta": "Aerobic, glucose-respiring bacteria (aerobic respiration)", "optb": "Ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (chemolithotrophic bacteria)", "optc": "Photosynthetic cyanobacteria (phototrophic metabolism)", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An organism is completely dependent on atmospheric O2 for growth. This organism is", "opta": "osmotolerant", "optb": "acidophile", "optc": "facultative anaerobe", "optd": "obligate aerobe", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Microaerophilic bacteria are those which require", "opta": "21 % oxygen for growth", "optb": "low levels of oxygen for growth (lesser than O2 present in atmosphere)", "optc": "oxygen for activation of enzymes", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The period between inoculation of bacteria in a culture medium and beginning of multiplication is known as", "opta": "stationary phase", "optb": "log phase", "optc": "lag phase", "optd": "decline phase", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term aerotolerant anaerobe refers to an organism that", "opta": "doesn't use oxygen but can grow in the presence of oxygen", "optb": "is killed by oxygen", "optc": "requires less oxygen than is present in air", "optd": "prefers to grow without oxygen", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The term obligate anaerobe refers to an organism that", "opta": "doesn't use oxygen but tolerates it", "optb": "is killed by oxygen", "optc": "uses oxygen when present or grows without oxygen when oxygen is absent", "optd": "prefers to grow without oxygen", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fragmentation occurs in", "opta": "Streptomyces species", "optb": "Nocardia species", "optc": "Bacillus subtilis", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}